Benjamin Irving Rouse Archives
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
Benjamin Irving Rouse Archives
1930-2006
ANTAR.000001
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
100
The archives of Benjamin Irving Rouse, accumulated during his time at Yale.
Rouse, Benjamin Irving
Biographical Sketch
(Benjamin) Irving Rouse (b. 1913, d. 2006) began his career at Yale as an undergraduate in forestry and switched to archaeology while a student employee of the Peabody's Anthropology Division. Intending to go into forestry, Ben Rouse did his undergraduate work in plant science at the Yale's Sheffield Scientific School, but a chance event changed his life and shaped his career.
"When I arrived at Yale in 1930, I put what little money my family was able to give me after the stock market crash the previous year into a bank; the bank went broke, so I had to support myself. Yale had a job placement bureau that gave me a couple of jobs raking leaves in the fall. Then they sent me to Cornelius Osgood, who had just arrived at Yale and discovered that less than half the archeological specimens at the Peabody Museum had been catalogued. Cataloguing those specimens was the first decent job offered to me. At Osgood's urging I started taking graduate courses in anthropology. By my junior year, I had decided I didn't want to be a forester. Osgood persuaded me to come into the Yale graduate program and eventually he directed my dissertation."
In college, Rouse had been drawn towards taxonomy in botany, a mature field of study, but he shifted to the much younger discipline of anthropology because he saw a more urgent need for classification there. He completed his Ph.D. at Yale, and went on to become Charles J. MacCurdy Professor of Anthropology and Curator of Anthropology at the Yale Peabody Museum. At various times from 1938 through his retirement in 1984, Professor Rouse was curator, assistant curator, research associate and faculty affiliate. A pioneer in circum-Caribbean archaeology and a major contributor to the development of archaeological methods, particularly ceramic analysis, typology and chronology, Rouse has left the Peabody Museum with the world's and most comprehensive systematically excavated collections from the Caribbean region, comprising 52 percent of the Division of Anthropology's catalog records and hundreds of thousands of individual objects, the largest and most important anthropology collections at the Peabody. Rouse and his colleagues and students excavated on most of the major islands in the Caribbean (Cuba, Haiti, Puerto Rico, Trinidad and others) as well as in Venezuela and Florida. He published several books and articles, including his 1999 publication with colleague and long-time research collaborator Birgit Faber Morse, Excavations at the Indian Creek Site, Antigua, West Indies. He was a member of the National Academy of Sciences, held important roles in national anthropological and archaeological organizations, and helped found the Archaeological Society of Connecticut.
Rouse's interest in the problems of classification was lifelong. His work combined two major themes in archaeological research: the distribution of culture over space and the study of culture change through time. The Peabody's 2005 Curator's Choice exhibition Detecting Cultures treated one small part of one excavation among many conducted by Rouse to reconstruct the prehistory of the Caribbean, where he has done so much groundbreaking work.
Rouse passed away in New Haven on February 4, 2006 at the age of 92.
Description of the Material
The Archives of Benjamin Rouse notably include materials used in the writing of his manuscripts, reserach files and numerous 35 mm slides of images from around the world.
Connecticut; Caribbean; Venezuela; Haiti; Cuba; Puerto Rico; Trinidad; Florida; Correspondence; Field notebooks; Manuscript materials; Maps; Photographs; Memorabilia; Yale Peabody Museum; Yale University
- Maps, 1930-2006; Series I
  - Base Maps. Includes maps from the Goode Base Maps Series, Nystrom Series of Desk Maps, American Geographical Society of New York, and McKinley's Geographical and Historical Outline Maps. Geographic areas include: South American, Caribbean, Southeast Asia, Austalasia, and World., 000364
  - Connecticut maps., 000250
  - Florida aerial photograph compliation maps. Series of maps compiled by the United States Coast Guards and Geodetic Survey from aerial photographs by the United States Army Air Corps. East coast of Florida., 000252
  - Jamaica - Office of Overseas Survey maps. Series of 12 topographic maps encompassing the entire country. (1:50,000)., 1959; 000321
  - Land Use in North Central Ifugao, Philippines. Maps: Land Use of North Central Ifugao; Harold Conklin, Yale University; American Geographical Survey, New York; 1972; Scale = 1:5,000; Universal Transverse Mercator Projection, Zone 51, Clarke 1866 spheroid. Series of 8 maps detailing the land use of North Central Ifugao, Philippines., 000165
  - Map of Hispanic America, American Geographical Society of New York. Map of Hispanic America series published between 1922 and 1943. Scale = 1:1,000,000., 1922-1943; 000040
  - Maps of Venezuela from Army Map Service. 9 maps of Venezuela from Army Map Service. A.M.S. series E884., 1946; 000237
  - Miscellaneous maps., 000143
  - Other Caribbean Maps. Individual maps of the Caribbean region., 000367
  - Other Cuba maps. Individual maps of Cuba., 000341
  - Other Georgia, Florida, and Bahamas maps. Assorted individual maps of Georgia, Florida, and the Bahamas., 000260
  - Other Hispaniola maps. Individual maps of Haiti and Dominican Republic., 000336
  - Other Japan maps. Individual maps of Japan., 000362
  - Other Puerto Rico maps. Individual maps of Puerto Rico., 000295
  - Other South America maps. Contains individual maps of South America., 000379
  - Other Southeast Asia maps. Individual maps of the Southeast Asia region., 000370
  - Other Trinidad maps. Individual maps of Trinidad., 000316
  - Other Venezuela maps. Individual maps of Venezuela., 000247
  - Plant maps. A series of maps illustrating the spread of various edible plants around the world through time. Includes 16 maps and four page document of explanations and corrections of the maps., 000144
  - Puerto Rico USGS maps. 48 United States Geological Survey maps. 7 1/2' quadrangle series., 000270
  - State maps of Venezuela. Venezuela; Prof. G. de-Agostini, Milano; Scale varies. (Maps in Spanish) Consists of 24 individual state maps and 1 map country of Venezuela., 000174
  - United Fruit Co. property maps, Cuba. Blueprint maps., 1939-1940; 000347
  - Venezuela - British Guiana Boundary Arbitration Atlases., 1898; 000162
  - [Untitled], 036383
  - Antilles., 036384
  - Brazil., 036386
  - Caribbean., 036388
  - Central America., 036389
  - Colombia., 036390
  - Costa Rica., 036391
  - Ecuador., 036392
  - Haiti., 036393
  - Martinique., 036394
  - Mexico., 036395
  - Peru., 036396
  - Puerto Rico., 036397
  - South America., 036398
  - United States., 036399
  - Trinidad., 036400
  - Venezuela., 036401
  - West Indies., 036402
  - Bahamas., 036408
  - Jamaica., 036410
  - Africa., 036428
  - Japan., 036430
- Correspondence, 1930-2006; Series II
  - Correspondence. One archive box; reviews, revisions, obituaries, artifact research., 042153
  - Correspondence. One archive box; artifact research, revisions, Japan trips., 042185
- Research Materials, 1930-2006; Series III
  - Antigua., 1930-2006; 034147
  - Cuba., 1930-2006; 034148
  - Haiti., 1930-2006; 034149
  - Misc. Caribbean Countries., 1930-2006; 034150
  - Puerto Rico., 1930-2006; 034144
  - Research card file. One file cabinet, 9 drawers, 3x5 slips. Rouse research notes on Caribbean and World Archaeology., 035884
  - Trinidad., 1930-2006; 034146
  - United States., 1930-2006; 034143
  - Venezuela., 1930-2006; 034145
  - Rouse - Ceramic Classifications., 035910
  - Africa., 036065
  - Antilles., 036069
  - Bahamas., 036072
  - Caicos., 036074
  - China., 036079
  - Greece., 036123
  - Asia., 036125
  - Japan., 036148
  - Micronesia., 036150
  - Dominican Republic., 036153
  - Research Materials Applicable to Multiple Sites., 039785
  - Middle East., 042220
- Photographs, 1930-2006; Series IV
  - Rouse - Aruba., 035894
  - Rouse - Brazil., 035895
  - Rouse - Colombia., 035896
  - Rouse - Connecticut., 035897
  - Rouse - Costa Rica., 035898
  - Rouse - Greater Antilles., 035899
  - Rouse - Guiana., 035900
  - Rouse - Ecuador., 035902
  - Rouse - Nicaragua., 035903
  - Rouse - Puerto Rico., 035904
  - Rouse - Peru., 035905
  - Rouse - Tobago., 035906
  - Rouse - Trinidad., 035907
  - Rouse - Venezuela., 035908
  - Rouse - West Indies., 035909
  - Rouse - Dominican Republic., 035963
  - Rouse - Haiti., 035965
  - Rouse - Cuba, Havana., 035967
  - Rouse - Pennsylvania., 035969
  - Rouse film archives., 041139
  - Rouse - Miscellaneous Photographs., 042231
- Manuscript Materials, 1930-2006; Series V
  - A Survey of Indian River Archaeology, Florida - figures. Includes map of Indian River area (Figs. 10 & 11) and copies of maps of the area. Also, copy of map from "Derrotero" and translation., 1951; 000319
  - An Archaeological Chronology of Venezuela. Original material from the publication including figures and plates., 000199
  - Antigua - Indian Creek site. Sketches of excavations 1 through 5 from July 1973. Two sheets of drawings of pottery pieces., 000309
  - Archeology of the Maniabon Hills, Cuba - figures. All of the original figures from publication except no.6. Nos.1, 4, and 9 also have earlier drafts., 1942; 000340
  - Cultural Sequence in Southwest Haiti - figures. Contains Figure 5., 1984; 000361
  - Culture of the Ft. Liberte Region, Haiti - figures. Original figures from publication., 1941; 000353
  - Excavations in the Ft. Liberte Region, Haiti - figures. Original figures from publication., 000352
  - Excavations on Upper Matecumbe Key, Florida - figures. Original figure no. 3., 1949; 000320
  - Frontiers Article - final figures. Need to determine which publication this is from., 000373
  - Introduction to Prehistory, A Systematic Approach - figures. Contains all of the original figures and tables from the book., 1972; 000374
  - On the Excavation of a Shell Mound at Palo Seco, Trinidad, B.W.I. - figures. Contains sections of excavation trenches, site map and map of Trinidad., 1919-1953; 000314
  - Prehistory in Haiti, A Study in Method - figures. Original figures from publication., 1939; 000354
  - Prehistory in Haiti, A Study in Method - page proofs. Contains the page proofs for the publication., 1939; 000355
  - Prehistory of the West Indies - figures. Original figures nos.1-5 from publication with several iterations of fig.2., 1 May 1964; 000372
  - Seriation in Archaeology - reprint plates. Contains original photgraphs of pages and printing plates for reprints., 1967; 000375
  - The Circum-Caribbean Theory, An Archaeological Test - figures. Contains original figures 1 and 2., Apr 1953; 000376
  - The Olsen Collection from Ile a Vache, Haiti - plates. Original plates from article., December 1982; 000334
  - Unknown Caribbean publication - figures. Contains draft maps of Caribbean cultures and Rouse timeline of Caribbean cultures. Two elevation views of excavations in La Salina, State of Sucre. Also two figures by Cruxent from 2/3/65 of Dominican Republic and Caribbean., 000311
  - Unknown Connecticut publication - figures. Illustrations, maps, and plates from unknown publication., 000304
  - Unknown Jamaica excavation. Excavation layout map from Bengal estate - Rio Bueno by Francis J. Osborne, S.J., 000360
  - Unknown Puerto Rico publication - figures. Illustrations and site maps from Puerto Rico publication., 000302
  - Unknown Venezuela publication - figures. Consists of two figures showing elevation views of trench locations at Abalon and La Columbina sites in La Salina, State of Sucre., 000313
  - Unkown Trinidad publication. Contains site map and profile of excavation trench from St. John site. Also, two Rouse timelines., 000315
  - OVERSIZED: "Migrations in PreHistory", Yale University Press Anthropology catalog and book cover printout., 036359
  - OVERSIZED: Drafts and extra copies of text, tables and charts for Chronology revision. 18 p., 036360
  - OVERSIZED: "Cultural Sequence in Southwestern Haiti." "Figure 3 (final)," 4 p. some duplicates., 036361
  - OVERSIZED: "Illustrations for article on Peopling of the New World 5/10/76." Correspondence, charts & transparencies of & regarding article illustrations 12 sheets/pages (some stuck together.)., 036362
  - OVERSIZED: 3 pages from Life magazine article: "The Treasure of Sutton Hoo."., 036364
  - OVERSIZED: "Inference of Migration from the Archeological Record" slide captions 2p (duplicate)., 036365
  - OVERSIZED: "Original drawings for Bulletin 24; A.S. of C." 6 cut boards with original sketches & glassine cover sheets (extra board) plus 2 photo cut-out mock ups of sketches for article illustration., 036366
  - OVERSIZED: 13 illustration plates plus 2 handwritten notes., 036367
  - OVERSIZED: "(K.Z.to) Scientific Societies Miscellaneous notes etc. ps" 2 newspaper articles re finds; atlas ad, drawing of pot by Bullbrook., 036368
  - "Japan Trip: Final report" - 2 copies of "Japan Society for the Promotion of Science, Tokyo"; handwritten version; "Provisions of the JSPS Research Fellowship" copy., 042240
- Biographical Materials, 1930-2006; Series VI
  - Curriculum Vitae and Bibliographies., 042149
  - Miscellaneous., 033813
- Memorabilia, Series VII
  - Aves Dominicanas. Reproductions of original drawings of Dominican birds. From the Dominican Development Fund. Six paintings. (translated from Spanish)., 1978; 000335
  - El Museo del Barrio. Poster and serigraph by Gilberto. From original packaging: Museo del Barrio, poster and painting 11/18/1982., 1981-1982; 000300
  - Japanese calendars. Japanese calendars featuring historic paintings., 000305
  - Newspapers from Antigua. Contains three newspapers: Antigua Times, May 16, 1973; The Worker's Voice, May 26, 1973; Antigua Star, June 2, 1973., 000318
  - Posters. Eclectic collection of Anthropology related posters from around the world., 000312
  - Ceremony Memorabilia., 036189
- Slides, Series VIII
  - Aegean., 013794
  - Africa., 013792
  - Amazonia., 013796
  - Antilles., 013793
  - Japan., 013798
  - MesoAmerica., 013795
  - Mesopotamia., 013797
  - Miscellaneous., 024897
  - North America., 013791
  - Oceania., 023045
  - Temperate East., 023044
  - Throlberia., 024348
  - Venezuela., 013790
- Reprint Collection, Series IX
  - Caribbean Reprint Collection. 12 labeled boxes. Caribbean reprints. alphabetical., 035875
  - Non-Caribbean Reprint Collection., 034124
- Teaching Materials, 1930-2006; Series X
  - Coursework and Academic Seminars., 036183
- Miscellaneous, 1930-2006; Series XI
  Scope and Contents
  Needs to be catalogued.
  - "Japan Trip: General" - 2 brochures; handwritten notecards; business cards; pages of correspondence., 042239